The amount of stuff that you learn about
what was going on at that time is just
mind-boggling.
>> This is Casey Muratori, video game
developer and sometimes computer
historian through his popular talks and
I asked them all about the stories in
computing he uncovered.
>> Dystro was depressed at that time.
>> He literally says like in this period I
was very depressed because of these
reasons. Look at the correspondence.
They didn't have the ability to do like
piffy Twitter replies, so it was just on
paper.
>> What drew you towards video gaming?
>> There's a bunch of things I could say
about that, but they're probably all BS.
Here's the full episode.
There's so much, you know, AI Doom
content out there. I'm hoping that we
can just talk about interesting things
in software engineering and just see
where it goes. So I'm not going to ask
anything that's uh you know all this AI
doom you're gonna you have two years
left to be a software engineer. So
>> fantastic. I will try to keep the AI
mentions to a minimum. [laughter]
>> There's this famous quote by Donald
Kuth. The big part of it is premature
optimization is the root of all evil.
And I remember I've I've heard that
before, but I I don't think I know the
full history behind it. And you know,
why is that significant?
So I guess we can split that into two
parts. Like what's the history behind it
and why is this significant? The
significant part is probably the easiest
to answer because it's, you know, for
whatever accident of history, it's
something that people really remembered
like it's stuck. And so the reason that
it ended up being significant is people
keep repeating it and they keep
interpreting it or reinterpreting it. So
the effects of that phrase far beyond
what anyone may have done with it in
context at the time or what they meant
or any of those things or the history,
the effects of it are like still felt to
this day. Some people uh I think
probably correctly you might say
interpret the term with a fair bit of
nuance and and say like oh well you know
it can mean a number of different things
or it's trying to capture something
subtle or whatever. Other people are
very blunt about it and just think like
oh it just means I don't have to think
about the performance of my code till
like the end of the project right like
like premature just means any
consideration of performance is not
worth it. eventually we'll see where the
code is slow and we'll fix it or
something, right? And so, uh, it's it's
a significant phrase for that reason, at
least to me. You still hear it to this
day and it's at least, you know,
depending on how, uh, you want to
account for it, it's at least something
that's 50 years old now. Uh, and so
that's an incredibly lasting impact for
a rule of thumb or however you want to
look at it. So uh on the history side,
this was really uh when I decided to to
to do a talk on this, I knew I wanted to
do another computer history talk um
because I had given one before at at
this was at something called the better
software conference. It's you know
there's been two of them so far and at
the first one I did a history talk and I
wanted to do another history talk and
this was going to be like probably only
going to do two of these and this second
one. I wanted to do it on the history of
this phrase because when I started
looking into the history of this phrase
a while back, I found that there was
just a lot of stuff there that I didn't
know. And this is true. I mean, I guess
I would say every time I've ever looked
at computer history, every every time
I've go I I refer to it as dumpster
diving, but it's not it's not like that
makes it sound derogatory. I just think
but I think of that as kind of what I'm
doing but it's not really like it's
actually a very enjoyable experience uh
to go back through history and try to
pick pick through what happened. But um
so to do this talk I basically went and
tried to do a a pretty detailed you know
analysis of like how did this phrase end
up being put in print? You know what
were the worked examples at the time?
What were they thinking about? Why might
it have been said?
>> What did you learn in doing all that
research about these famous computer
science phrases? The thing that shocks
me, it shock it both times, even though
I've now done it twice, the amount of
stuff that you learn about what was
going on at that time that you just had
no idea is is just mind-boggling. And
and I would point out that this is for a
talk. You know, I'm not a historian. I
don't do this for a living. I'm not at a
university somewhere doing computer
history research. So what I think of as
a pretty thorough read for the history
that I did for the talk is actually
somewhat shallow. Like if you had time
and the resources, you could go access
some of these people's personal papers,
make appointments to see things that are
not really in the public record so much
and so on. So even just with publicly
available things that you can get, the
amount of stuff that I found was just
really kind of uh intriguing to me. And
so um I'll give like a kind of a brief
overview of sort of what what I thought
was the story of this kind of phrase in
a way. Um I think there are kind of two
I guess I would say there there are sort
of two threads that are good to
understand that come together and this
is what I tried to portray in the talk
as well.
The first thread is this idea um of a
thing and you know we didn't really do
an intro to this to this podcast but um
so I'll just I'll say it now. I'm a big
fan of your show. When when you said do
you want to be on the podcast you didn't
have to tell me what the show was. Like
I've already watched it. I I love it. Uh
and one of the people you had on for
example was Barbara Liskoff. And in that
interview she actually refers to
something called the software crisis.
Right. Um and I think you prompted or a
question about this as well. Right? So,
a lot of people don't really know about
the software crisis. They don't know
that that was a term. They don't know
this something that happened because
it's kind of ancient history now. It was
in the sort of late 60s, early 70s. This
was a thing. And what this was is
originally, you know, computer hardware
in a sense that you or I can't really
conceive of it in practice because it
was so far before our time, right?
um that basically computer hardware
originally was very simplistic. And so
the things that you were going to do
with it could be described very easily
and really all you were trying to do
when you programmed a computer was just
translate a fairly straightforward
definition of some computation into like
machine instructions.
The kind of thing that we would kind of
think about today as like hand
optimizing assembly code was really just
all computer programming kind of was,
right? It was just like, okay, we're
going to we're going to take this
problem description and and translate it
in.
But during the 60s, computing power was
advancing to the point where people
could consider doing much more
significant things with it. They could
run payroll systems. They could do
analysis of of data sets. and they would
want to be able to be flexible and
change the sorts of computations they
were doing and all these other sorts of
things. They were starting to have
graphical displays. Uh you know um Ivan
Southerntherland sketchpad is like in
the early 1960s, right? And so what they
found was at that time programmers were
not really ready to make that
transition. They didn't think about
things the way we kind of all now take
for granted where it's like, oh yeah,
you know, I built this library for
loading JPEG images and now when I want
to load a JPEG, I just call load JPEG
and it's done. And you know, all of
these things that we take for granted,
that all had to that all had to be a
cultural shift. The idea that there were
going to be these um abstractions and
these ways of of sort of breaking down a
much more complex system into parts that
we could manage, that actually was a
transition that had to happen. And so
the software crisis was kind of this
period where people were starting to say
the methods that we're using for
programming will not scale to these
larger problems that we want to do.
We've got to figure out something uh to
do about it. So that's one thread of
history that's coming. Another thread of
history that's coming that's you know
it's a little bit more specific to
Donald Kuth who was the first person to
really put this into a worked example.
like he's kind of who I would credit
with the origin of this phrase, even if
there are people who might debate that
fact. And to me, it doesn't really
matter who said the phrase, like the
phrase lives on in on its own. So, you
know, I I I wouldn't I wouldn't even
argue with someone if they wanted to
sort of uh make other claims about it.
But just in general,
he was going like like at Stanford at
this time, he was sort of learning about
the fact that you could do these
profiles like taking actual execution
profiles, figuring out where time was
spent in the execution of a program and
using that to guide your decision-m
about how where are you going to spend
time developing the software. Again,
something that even today today
performance is maybe not as much of an
emphasis as it maybe should be in
software, but even today with that in
mind, most people understand the concept
of an execution profile. They understand
that you could go into Chrome and see
like a network profile of how that's
working. You could uh see a flame graph
of of you know where time is being spent
or all these sorts of things.
Again, you have to remember if you
rewind the clock back far enough, these
were all brand new concepts, right? a
sampling profiler, a block brace
profiler, uh you know, a a binary
instrumentation profiler. All these
sorts of things were not just tools that
everyone assumed that they could just go
have and and had seen at some point.
Some people may never have even realized
that was was a thing, right?
So that's another thread that's
happening. And those two things converge
effectively in 1974 roughly to get us
this statement. Can is very much into
this idea of structured programming
which is sort of a a solution a proposed
solution to the software crisis.
Maybe a proposed solution is the wrong
way to say it. It's a certain set of
ideas that are trying to be employed to
improve the situation. Let's say he's
very much in into this and we can talk
about what that is uh sort of a separate
tangent if we want to later. He's very
much into that. He's thinking about
that. He's um he's thinking about this
idea that programmers can't just be
about writing all of this very tightly
optimized assembly language code and
that's all we're going to spend all our
time doing. We have to be thinking
bigger picture. We have to be picking
and choosing our battles. We have to
make concessions to maintainability. Uh
you know if this particular routine is
not really accounting for hardly any of
our runtime, we should not be obuscating
it with all of these like hand unrolling
the loops and all these things. Remember
again underlying all this they don't
have like massive optimizing compiler
kind of passes like we have with LLVM
now right they don't have all of this
extra stuff so if you wanted something
unrolled you were going to unroll it
yourself if you wanted some kind of loop
hoist a loop invariant out you probably
had to do that yourself like a lot of
that stuff that we take for granted
again not in there so um that sort of
this he's very unstructured programming
he's starting to see these execution
time profiles they do a thing at
Stanford in the n in in 1970 and he
actually he does it with some students
where they take a look at uh forrren
programs and they instrument them to see
where the time is being spent. Not in
exactly the most rigorous way that you
might imagine. That's another thing for
my talk that I kind of go into. Um but
he's sort of saying like look
we we as programmers need to start
taking the decision about what to
optimize more seriously.
And he kind of has a fairly nuanced take
on it. If you actually read the section
um of his 1974 paper uh structured
programming with go-to statements where
kind of the first time this was really
put to print that I know of he he does
he does say it in an ACM touring lecture
a little earlier but he would have
submitted like based on my timeline he
would have submitted the manuscript for
this publication prior to the lecture.
So it was the first time that I know of
that he actually committed it to paper
would have been there but he may have
said this a lot in lectures. He kind of
obliquely refers to that in the touring
lecture that maybe he had said this
around you know around town so to speak.
So you know where this was first uttered
I don't think anyone knows but point
being uh when he says that phrase kind
of it's in this context of saying look
we we need to be very concerned about
efficiency. We shouldn't be leaving
performance on the table when it
matters. But at the same time, we need
to know that it matters. If we don't
know that it matters that we're going to
apply this optimization, then you know
that's a premature optimization and it
has real costs. It it's going to make
our maintenance and debugging of this
program worse for all the same reasons
that it would make it worse today. Like
if we go into something and we start
applying these like optimizations to it
that are above and beyond the kind of
structural things that we might be doing
to that code otherwise that's creating a
cognitive burden right um that other
people are now going to have to deal
with and you're going to have to deal
with in the future. So I don't want to
put too many words in Canuth's mouth
certainly, but in general that's sort of
the way that this comes together is
those two things. This idea that we need
to be more, you know, be doing things to
solve the software crisis, have a more
structured appro approach to
programming, care about maintainability
and debugability, composability,
abstraction, all that stuff. But also at
the same time, we do care about
optimization. So how do you dovtail
those things? Premature optimization is
the root of all evil is kind of like
this phrase he uses. I I would I would
say if I had if I had to imagine his way
of sort of reminding himself, think
about all this before you make a
decision, right? Um
that would be kind of my take on it,
right? And and where it comes from. So
hopefully, I don't know, that's very
long, but it's a very expansive
question. So hopefully I've kind of
wrangled most of the stuff into there.
It sounds like this is really a
engineering trade-off where the software
crisis is about the maintainability and
uh the the complexity for people to
actually write and handle their code and
then the trade-off between performance
and I guess you know code that is
maintainable and it sounds like this new
quote is
you know be mindful of where you pay
that cost. Yes. And it's always
important to understand the context in
which this was said historically. It's
why I want it to be a historical talk
because who your audience is is a large
determiner of what the root of all evil
is. Right? If you talking if you're
talking to a bunch of people who don't
think about optimization at all, then
you don't really need to say this phrase
to them, right?
And so if you fast forward to today when
a lot of people don't really take
optimization into account at all during
their programming um or very very little
uh this phrase doesn't make very much
sense to someone who does care about
performance because like why would you
ever say that? It just kind of seems
like it encourages people to not be
mindful of the performance of their
program.
But if you rewind to that time
and you understand that well a lot of
the program you know they had the
opposite problem. A lot of the programs
at that time what what programming was
was coming up with all these crazy
little assembly tricks to like shave a
cycle off here or there, right? And if
you're talking to an auditorium full of
people who are really into that sort of
thing,
uh then it really can be the root of all
evil, right? It's like you guys are
spending all your time on this, but we
have this really big other problem and
that is not the right trade-off, right?
That is you've you've swung, you know,
like calling it trade-offs is a great
way to say it. You've swung the pendulum
way too far in one of those directions
at some point. And and so, you know, to
some degree, while I wouldn't while I
would highly dispute the the description
root of all evil today as a good thing
to say to somebody or or that it leaves
a good impression, when we rewind to
that time period, I think it makes a lot
more sense because when you look at what
people were actually spending their time
doing, where their priorities were, I
think that maybe that wasn't so much of
an exaggeration. I mean, obviously, it's
a hyperbole, but it's less of one. in
your slides, there were so many quotes
and snippets of really kind of digging
into the true history. Was there
anything you found that surprised you
when you were doing the research?
>> I mean, constantly. Uh, absolutely,
constantly. And I mean, first of all,
I'll just say that there's
as a meta point, I'll I'll give you a
specific thing that surprised me that's
kind of funny. Um, that's that's more
about like a technical thing. But first
I want to talk about a broader picture
which is one of the things that really
hits home for me whenever I do these is
the personal aspects of it like these
people were like friends and competitors
and like all these sorts of things and
it's all kind of lost to us in a way
when we think about computing history in
like a sterile way like you know when I
read up on what Dystra Dyster was the
person who kind of kicked off the
structured programming.
I don't want to call it a revolution.
That's a bit too probably grandiose, but
kicked off that train of thought. Say uh
he wrote a a thing called notes on
structured programming. It was a
manuscript or monograph. I don't I don't
remember what they called, you know, got
like a typewritten like it looks like
exactly like a typewriter written thing,
right? Um he when he wrote that he was
like very depressed like he was having a
lot of trouble in his life at that time.
He had he had gone through this this
situation where uh they had done what
people today now recognize as like
pioneering work in distributed computing
like he and these other uh people at the
Einhovven Technological University. I
don't I apologize I can't say the proper
name for it. It's it's you know it's
well beyond my pronunciation
capabilities. But point being um he had
done this really foundational work in uh
distributed computing and published it
and people today now recognize it as
that it is like undisputedly a massive
contribution to distributed computing.
He did it with a part-time team of
people at the university who this wasn't
their job. it was a mathematics
department they were in and you know as
a result of that uh basically they sort
of just got dissolved like the the
department of mathematics I guess like
he wasn't really specific about it but
in his notes like the department of
maths was just like they disbanded the
team he was like this you know this
isn't math or whatever I don't know they
just had a a pessimist view of it so um
and he was really depressed about that
and he wasn't sure what he should do
with his life and like you know what's
what what's the deal here right and he
was having this sort of um I don't want
to call it an existential crisis because
I don't want again put words in his
mouth. These are historical figures and
you know I can that's why I try to use
quotes to try to show you like what they
said. Um but like that's it's just so
relatable when you go through the
history this way. It it's not just some
random guy who wrote some math down in a
paper. It's like people were really
struggling with this and some of the
most important aspects of computer
history come out of these amazing human
stories. And I found that absolutely
fascinating. So, I'll just put that out
there as one of the biggest rewarding
things about looking into this history
if you ever do it is if you can go find
the actual writings of the people,
like things outside of just their
technical papers, it's just fascinating
and it's so much more relatable and
fascinating because you feel the story.
It's not just this abstract computation
uh computer science thing that happened.
So that's one thing.
But the other thing I was going to say
is like when you read through this
stuff, I'm just I just go through piles
of documents and I'm just reading them
and seeing, you know, does this fit into
this story? You know, should it be part
of what I'm telling or is it extraneous?
Is it something that, you know, uh is
interesting perhaps, but not actually
part of it? And one thing that I found I
when the VOD of this lecture uh or talk
goes up I'm going to uh include this in
the notes because I thought it was so if
it didn't make it into the talk I found
a thing
uh like a a uh thing from Tony
So, so Charles, Anthony, Richard
uh, who again is another massive figure
in computer science, right? Hora,
Dystra, and Canuth are like, you know,
the three amigos and like they they all
write to each other, right? And they're
very important people in computer
science history. So, um, I found a thing
by him that was like a a thing he did
not decide to pursue. It's like this
note where he's talking about, you know,
he's talking about this thing that he's
thinking of doing. And there's just a
handwritten thing on him from later on
in his life when he was I guess
categorizing these documents. And he
just writes down like I decided not to
pursue this because you know I I talked
about it at this conference that I was
at and Peter Nauer who's like again
another famous figure in computer
science history. If you've ever heard
the if you ever looked at um like
contextfree grammarss and parsing you've
probably heard Bakasau form. He's the
ner in Bakasnau form. If you ever heard
of the language Al Gallal, he was like a
major, you know, figure in in
standardizing that and writing up the
standard and all this stuff, right? So
anyway, Horus like yeah, I I proposed
this thing. I went through I said it and
like and Peter now was like ah making
multipass compilers is easy. I I just
wrote a nine pass one. So I was you know
I decided not to pursue this, right? So
what's the thing? I read through the
thing and like maybe I'm just
overreading it with the benefit of
hindsight, but he pretty much describes
static single assignment form like like
SSA
uh which is a very standard compiler
technique developed in the 80s but this
note is from the 60s. So it's like in my
head I'm like did Peter Nau accidentally
set back like computer like like
compiler science by 20 years by like
telling Tony well 15 let's say by
telling Tony like this is not
important when actually was would have
been like very very important. So uh you
find stuff like that all the time where
you're like whoa what is this? I I saw
another one too. Uh just one more I'll
mention.
Uh I I can't remember now. I'm sorry. Uh
again, your brain kind of turns to mush
when you try to dump this many documents
into it for a talk. Uh uh there was a a
pretty interesting thing I thought where
uh uh Margaret Hamilton so the the
person who you know managed the Apollo
she was she was you know one of the core
programmers originally on the project
and then then was like the man like the
manager of the whole OS like the whole
like real-time software that ran the
Apollo 11 well all the Apollo uh flight
computer stuff right
which I mean most people today herald is
like a very very significant like
real-time systems like achievement in
that era, right? Like everyone pretty
much agrees uh with that
she had to write like a defense. I think
it was in the AC the communication to
the ACM maybe it was in data like they
say apologize I can't remember the venue
because like it had been pointed out as
like a failure because people didn't
understand the context that like the
reason that the Apollo computer had to
like trip those alarms was because that
it had been used improperly like it was
used in a configuration it wasn't
supposed to and it actually rather than
crashing went into backup modes and
successfully landed like it it worked
like it it actually was a triumph of
like fault tolerant engineering and she
had to write like a defense of this
because people at the time were saying
like oh that they screwed up like this
is an example of of how why you wouldn't
want to do engineering this way or like
you know don't write the code this way
and so um again stuff like that always
makes me think like the more things
change the more they stay the same
exactly what would happen on Twitter now
right like like some very successful
thing that people did right they would
just get like slandered and say that it
was done wrong and there would be like a
flame war and then they'd have to come
out and have a thing, you know. So,
anyway, uh those are just some examples,
but there's so much great stuff in
there. I highly recommend anyone who
likes this kind of thing, you won't be
disappointed if you go if you go
dumpster diving, as I call it.
>> When you said that you saw the human
stories and that Dystra was depressed at
that time, what did you see that made
you realize that?
>> One of the nice things about Dystra is
that he's kind of a pretty straight
shooter. And so I didn't actually have
to do any interpretation. He literally
talks about like being depressed. And
like he has like a there's a paper uh
not a paper like a thing that he did
that's like a retrospective
um on that's like handwritten by him
later on in life and he literally says
like in this period I was very depressed
because of these reasons. Now he could
be wrong about the source of his
depression, right? Uh, so I don't want
to claim that that just because he said
it it's ne necessarily true or something
like that. But one of the amazing things
I I think one of the the really cool
things about academics
uh especially that era is they just
produced a voluminous amount of material
and so we don't have to guess that much
in the private sector. I think it'd be a
lot harder like if you wanted to know uh
what people at you know maybe
you know Lockheed or something were
thinking or doing at that time I imagine
it's much more difficult just because
you know things are classified or
they're not academics so they're not
necessarily going to write them all up
uh you know so a lot of the internal
stuff when we read up academics don't
really have that they don't have an
incentive or a prohibition on writing up
everything they do so they don't just
have to have like a public-f facing
statement of what they did or a public
facing paper of what they and then oh
there's this extra secret stuff. The
academics don't have that restriction.
They're sort of they benefit from being
as forthcoming as possible about what
they've accomplished. Usually
>> I saw in the in the slides that you
looked at go to considered harmful that
FEMA. Do you have any sense of the the
personal or people side of that?
[laughter]
Uh, so you're talking about the original
like Dystra letter to the editor that's
like Ed's Gdystra go-to cons uh
statement considered harmful. This okay
um the complete story is actually
relatively simple. He according to him
he was at a uh at a conference um uh in
Tennessee
where he was talking to Brian Randelle
who's another computer science guy. um
he he doesn't quite get the same level
of uh name recognition as a canth or
something like that. Uh but he has a lot
of papers at that time. Like you can go
find him. He's not an obscure he's not
an obscure figure. I wouldn't say uh to
anyone who reads the history. You'll see
him come up. He's talking to Brian
Randell and some other people outside.
This is exactly like the same thing that
happens at modern conferences. There's
like the talks and then there's all the
stuff that goes down at the bar, right?
It's it's very much that they're
outside. talking
and according to him he's basically
giving the same sort of example of a
problem with the goto that he gives in
the paper right this idea of enumeration
we can talk about that later if but um
but the sort of a side note
he's sort of saying like here this is
kind of a problem with with goto and one
of the reasons that maybe it's not such
a good idea and the people who are
listening to him were like you know
Brian and the others were like you
should p like you should publish that
that would be helpful because you know
there's these arguments going on about
whether goto is good or bad like that
was kind of happening at the time
already uh since since around 1959 even
I think there'd kind of been a little
bit of that had been kind of growing
this idea that maybe go-to statements
weren't weren't um the best idea
uh as a way to structure your programs
and so he does he goes back to Einhovven
and he writes up this same thing he
saying basically and he sends it to to
communications of the ACM for
publication.
uh Nicholas Worth who is like the
creator of Pascal right a very prominent
figure also uh was very heavily involved
in alol and all this sort of stuff like
you know language designer guy he is the
editor uh who is in charge of like
getting this getting this thing
published I guess I'm not exactly sure
how things work at at the communications
of the ACM
he doesn't want to wait to have it
published he doesn't want to take the
time to like go through the referee
process or whatever. I don't know like
at that time what the requirements were
for publishing a article in
communications with the ACM but I'm sure
that it involved a lot of procedure.
wasn't just like, "Oh, hey, I'm, you
know, I'm the creator of Pascal."
Although that that time he wouldn't have
been the creator of Pascal yet because
Pascal comes later, I think, but but
either way, he's like, "Hey, I'm this
important guy. I'm just going to put
this whatever I want communication."
That's not how it worked. And so he
decides that in order to get it
published more quickly, he's just going
to publish it as a letter to the editor
because then there's no pro like any,
you know, anything goes there as long as
the editors are fine with the content, I
assume. Like it doesn't have to be
refereed, doesn't have to have any kind
of review, it doesn't have to uh etc,
etc.
So, he turns it into a letter to the
editor and he takes the name of the
thing that Dystra sent, which was a case
against the go-to statement. That was
what Dyster wrote at the top of the
thing as the title. He changes it for
letters to the editor to Edgar Dystra
go-to statement considered harm or
considered harmful. Right?
So, it wasn't it wasn't even Dyster's
plan to like have it maybe be that
confrontational,
but that's what happens. Um, now this is
not
wellreceived to say the least. Uh, the
according to can
uh again I'm just trying to say who said
what here. According to Canuth, Dystra
said he got letters like like angry like
threatening letters like uh in much the
same way you would today, right? Like he
got got people who were uh very abusive
and at you know telling him off
and I'm sure part of that is because by
all accounts Dystra himself was also
somebody who liked to push people's
buttons. That's well acknowledged. Um I
think Alan Kay is probably the best
source for this. He talks about uh this
uh he liked Dystra and they apparently
got along well, but you know he he's
often said that Dystra was someone who
kind of leaned into the being uh sort of
brash about stating things about
programming and uh and kind of relished
that position. So it probably didn't
help that he was already sort of known a
little bit in that way. But in general
that's that's how it went down. And
[clears throat]
like I said, that wasn't the initial
foray against goto statements by any
stretch of the imagination, but it it
just kind of
maybe you call it the straw that broke
the camel's back. It was like a it was
like a flash point might be the way to
say it. And so, and then the title of
course be that Nicholas Berth picked uh
is quite the doozy and kind of
clickbaited everyone, you know, as I
call it into that.
It's funny. Yeah. Cuz I mean your social
media, it's similar patterns, right?
People have very explosive first lines
and then the comments are full of all
this [laughter] hate and stuff. In in
their case, I'm guessing this is all
papers. So you submit a letter to that.
It's a physical thing and people are
reading uh
>> maybe a newspaper or something. I don't
know what.
>> Yeah, it's like a periodical like it
comes, you know, as a bound. I mean, I
guess there's all the things around us
here are hard bound, but it's like
usually was soft. It was a you know
maybe a perfect binding uh kind of bound
thing that has you you open it up table
of contents and letters editor right and
uh yeah like you can go find there are
there are a few if you go look at
people's personal papers which like like
I said if I did this full-time I'm sure
I could find out way more stuff than I
did right
but some people have gone and looked at
the personal papers and occasionally
some of them have been able to digitize
some of those and put them online that
we can look at and you can find for
example online right now if you search
for it uh
there's a there's a back and forth
letters personal letters between Dystra
and a guy who is kind of into functional
programming and promoting that and like
you can look at the correspondence and
it's kind of it's a little it's a little
flame worry like like it it really like
that's what they did they they didn't
have the ability to do like pathy
Twitter replies So it was just on paper.
Uh and yeah and Canuth did something
similar. It wasn't really a flame
because he had a at least when reading
it comes through as a tremendous amount
of respect for the authors of the book
structured programming which is uh
Dystra and doll. Um he you know
one of the things that he published was
a series of open letters to them
reviewing the book and talking about the
things that he didn't find compelling in
it. Right? like very respectful. So, it
wasn't that one wasn't a a flame war.
But that's what they Yeah, that's what
they had to do because they didn't have
social media. So, you know, Edgar
Dystra's uh he wrote like all these
things called EWD with a number. It was
it was his initials basically. Um and
then a number and that's like this like
serialized list of all the things he
wrote. And he like labels them this way.
Like it's not like some historian
characterized it after the fact. just
like, "Oh, I'm doing a He's like, "I'm
doing EWD 937 now." or whatever, right?
It's hilarious. Uh, but anyway,
several of those have been put online
that are not necessarily technical.
Like, for example, his trip reports. You
can go read those and you can read about
like, oh, like I went and I went and
stayed at like such and such's house and
like we went to dinner or whatever,
right? So, you can find like some nice
personal anecdotes in even the publicly
available stuff. But in terms of like a
real like heart-to-heart conversation, I
didn't have access to anything like that
that wouldn't have just been in a paper
more or less normally. Um, so, you know,
it's it's a shame. One of the problems
with this stuff, it's so interesting,
but it's not a job to do. Like, it's
like if somehow it was a job, I probably
would almost take that job. like like
being the person who crawls through and
tries to like redo this whole thing.
But, you know, computer historian, no
one's no one's hiring. Like that's not
no one's interested in paying for that.
So,
>> you have this other talk and the title
was just so catching. It was the big
oops anatomy of a 35-year mistake.
>> Yes.
>> What is that 35-year mistake?
>> Um, so this was a this was a kind of
funny thing that happened to me that I
uh then did a historical lecture on I
I had worked on systems in the past that
were basically like editors like you
know you have to m like three 3D
graphics editors like you have to multi
select things and move them around and
there's a bunch of like architecture
things you have to learn to be able to
write that kind of code and and certain
kinds of problems you have to solve like
a a very basic one that I would point
out that hopefully most people can
relate to would be if I have a bunch of
things on the screen. Uh some of which
have a color. So maybe maybe this is a
drawing program and I've got some text
and I've got some shapes and I've got um
some uh strokes, you know, some some
handdrawn stuff, whatever. And I want to
be able to to select a bunch of them and
I want the user interface to present to
me which things I could edit on these
shapes. So I want to be able to edit the
color and I want it to apply to all of
them. Right? This is just a basic
architectural problem that you have to
solve if you're going to write one of
these programs and you want it to be any
good. oftentimes you will see programs
where the person didn't solve this
problem and you can't do that. It's very
frustrating, right? So a good program
someone has solved that architectural
problem in some way
and I was watching um I just happened to
be watching because sometimes I do like
I like to watch old videos of computer
science pioneer stuff and I was watching
a a demo of Sketchpad. I'd seen it
before, but I was watching a de demo of
Ivan Southern Sketchpad. And Sketchpad,
for those who don't know, is a
groundbreaking computer graphics
program. It's done with a light pen. Uh,
and it was done in the early 60s. And
you could draw things like you do in a
modern CAD program and you could do
stuff that even a lot of modern CAD
programs don't really offer or only
offered recently. I think in the talk I
said in 2007 was the first time that
like AutoCAD got some of these features.
You could do stuff like say these two
shapes like this line has to be
perpendicular to that line, constrain
it, and you could just do whatever you
want with the drawing and it would like
resolve for like making that happen. And
these are very rare in programs even to
this day. Like that's just not a common
operation you would see in a drawing
package today. So [clears throat]
I was looking at this and I was like,
how the heck did he solve this
architectural problem? like how did he
do this stuff in the early 1960s like in
assembly language with no editing tools,
no debugging tools. I mean, this would
have been like, you know, either punch
cards or one step away from punch cards.
Like, it it would have been hard to
develop this stuff.
And when I went back and I went through
his thesis and I looked at the code,
it's actually documented how he did it.
And I realized like, oh crap, this is
actually like an entity component system
basically like what we would now
consider sort of stateofthe-art
of real time architecture for doing
these kind of operations meaning
crosscutting like operating on this kind
of property across many things at once
that are all kind of different.
And this was something that
object-oriented programming, I'm
editorializing now. Bunch of people will
complain that I'm saying this, but this
is just my opinion. Object-oriented
programming and the pedagogy around it
really struggled with that problem for a
long time because there were teaching
despite people who will now claim
otherwise. I document it very completely
in the talk. So I I don't think they
have any leg to stand on. But the
pedagogy at the time was all about build
a domain model. The domain model looks
like your hierarchy basically like I've
got employees and employees I've got
contractors and I've got derived like is
this a full-time employee or a part-time
employee like that was how they
suggested these things should be
implemented right and that kind of
architecture doesn't work for these
kinds of operations that I'm talking
about identity component systems do and
generally that kind of sort of uh
rotated architecture I might call it uh
does work for these.
And so what I call the 35 mistake is the
fact that
I very ironically in my opinion
sketchpad sort of showed in its
architecture how you could solve this
problem and how you could solve it in
arguably an object-oriented way. I think
if you squint at it, a person who does
object-oriented programming could easily
make an argument that you could do an
object-oriented version of this. You
don't have to violate any particular
principles to do it. It's just not the
hierarchy domain model way that people
were conceptualizing it through a lot of
the, you know, 80s and 90s, let's say,
and even unfortunately to this day, but,
you know, I think a lot of object
ordering programs don't do that anymore.
Ironically, that was in Sketchpad. The
DNA was there and we could have had it
right away because Ivan Sutherland
figured it out. But weirdly enough, the
whole idea of this sort of uh
inheritance hierarchy with lots of
encapsulation around it
grew in part out of Sketchpad because
like Alan K looked at it and said like,
"Oh, the interesting part of this is the
fact that you could take a a shape and
not know what it was and just have this
like draw a circle call on it or
something." That was the part they took
away from it, which is much less
interesting in my opinion and not that
architecturally useful in most cases.
So in kind of this amusing way,
Sketchpad contained in if if you know
I'm editorializing it contained what I
consider to be a good architectural
idea, but the takeaway from it was a bad
architectural idea is is how I would say
it. And saying bad architectural idea is
a little bit strong because as I say in
the talk, I think there are times when
you do want to think like a very high
level, you might want to think about
things in kind of the way that you know
small talk thinks about them. Um, so I
don't want to say bad idea in the
absolute sense, but bad in the way it
ended up being uh, you know, applied,
let's say.
>> Why is that class hierarchy not work for
this problem?
>> It's it's pretty easy to understand
actually. So when you think through an
inheritance hierarchy that's based on
sort of what you see in the real world
or what you're trying to model. So you
say like uh the typical example and it's
brought up tons of times by uh people
who wrote the oop literature like be
true strip uh like the small talk people
is the idea is uh keeping it with a
sketch pad example I'm going to have a
shape from the shape I'm going to derive
like triangle or circle and the
encapsulation is around that thing. So a
circle has a radius but shapes don't
have radiuses. shapes don't necessarily
know what that is, right? So, it tends
to get deferred down and the
encapsulation boundary is drawn around
that sort of derived class that's like
the most derived version of whatever
this thing is, right?
The problem is that creates a lot of
headaches when now something that wants
to work across a lot of shapes needs to
actually do something intelligent with
modifying say the scale of something or
wanting to change its color because it
doesn't really have a way to know what's
going on in these highly encapsulated
things.
So typically what you end up having to
do in those sit in those situations is
you then have to take this inheritance
hierarchy and kind of in a sense throw
away the benefits of it. you end up
having to make at the top all of these
accessor iterator things that allow you
to probe into that like lower class and
say tell me all of the colors that you
might be using and a name for them,
right? Or and so in a sense what you end
up having to do when you want the
architecture to work is you have to
rebuild the sketchpad version on top of
the inheritance hierarchy version which
doesn't really do anything for you,
right? And it's not to say that there
isn't some benefit that you can derive
from having derived is kind of a pun
here I guess that you can derive from
having this idea of saying this thing is
like this other thing. Please give me
some of the implementation of it. That's
not necessarily a bad thing in practice.
The problem is when you teach people
that this is how it's going to work.
Like you just make this hierarchy and
then your architecture is just supposed
to work. it really illprepares them for
the reality that like that's actually
not going to solve most of most of the
problems that you have are not going to
be solved that way. Um and again it just
comes from this fact that typically when
we're working with computer programs
most of the time what we need to do is
create crosscutting operations that work
with a lot of the data that's inside
these derived classes. that's actually
the thing that we want to do and it's
really cumbersome and typically a bad
fit for the problem space to put that
into some virtual functions that are
sitting at the top of this very uh sort
of tall hierarchy. It's usually much
better to do uh again even if you're
doing object programming you don't have
to stop doing objecting program you just
have to think about it differently you
have to think about what the objects are
differently uh where you're drawing the
encapsulation boundaries it just helps
to think about it differently and say
actually the more important things to
model are what are the things that stuff
is built out of how do I build a circle
out of objects right what are those
things a radius property a center
property those maybe should be the
objects that I'm thinking of as more
first class citizens and this
inheritance hierarchy stuff about what
the objects are that I see on the screen
like triangle and circle that's a
distraction that's not the proper way to
model the problem um and again I don't
think I would be pissing off any
object-oriented programmers by saying
that today because I think a lot of them
use architectures that do think about
objects in that sort of rotated sense
and not in the domain model hierarchy
sense not that there aren't still people
who are doing that but you know It's
it's not the only way to to go nowadays.
It's not the only way it's promulgated.
Yeah, because I guess my immediate
thought would have been in in that case
the the base class has the notion of a
color or some shared thing and we just
operate if you're a shape then we assume
you have a color and we but you're
saying refactoring and putting up in
there's suboptimal and there's you want
all these uh subasses to have some
handle to some radius property or
something like that. is that
>> what you just described is what tends to
happen in systems that are architected
this way. you end up with your derived
class not really being very much of
anything because in order to edit stuff
you had to migrate it all up to the top
and that there was actually terms for
this uh in the old days I don't still
use like fatty base classes right are
things like that's like it just ends up
your base class has like every type of
property that any derived class might
ever have like you have like get primary
color get secondary color get tertiary
color get right because it's like
something needed three different colors
or whatever uh and most things don't use
those colors and all these other sorts
of things
And so um there's certainly nothing
wrong with running a program that way.
It's just again why did you bother with
the hierarchy? Like you're not getting
any actual encapsulation benefits from
it because you just forced everything to
the base class anyway. So why didn't you
just make that be your thing? Just make
one class called shape and be done.
Right? So uh in terms of the the ECS
style of implementation and I don't
necessarily want to advocate for it or
not because uh I I don't actually
personally use ECS's or anything like
that but they are very common. Now
the idea there is to just turn it on its
side and say look typically what we want
to do is do things like okay there's
stuff that has like physics on it like
you know I'm I'm doing this thing and
and I want to have like physical
simulation of of entities. Well, the
physics system is the thing that
probably knows how that should be
stored. So rather than having that be
data in my derived class that is
encapsulated around the derived class.
Instead, why don't I just have the
physics system knows what physics is.
And then if you want to make something
that participates in physics, you just
have a handle for whatever this thing
is, like a handle for my shape. That
handle is valid in all the systems. So I
can go look up the physics properties of
the shape and gather it when I want to
actually do something with it. But
generally speaking, the encapsulation
stays around the system. So physics
properties are defined by the physics
system because hey, that's who knows how
physics should work and I just ask about
my physics when I need to do something
with it. And this kind of gets you out
of that problem. And then now you can
just compose things. Oh, I want to make
something that has several physics
elements in it. Fine. I can just have
multiple physics handles if that's what
I need or something like this. I can
very flexibly like merge these things
together. I want something to not have
physics. I just don't ever insert the,
you know, I don't ever ask the physics
system to have a valid, you know, piece
of data for this handle in it and it
won't simulate any physics for it.
Right? Whether that's the world's best
architecture or not, I'm not going to
argue for it or against it. It's just
it's a lot better than domain model
hierarchies. That I will say, right?
OpenAI, Enthropic, Cursor, and Verscell
all use this product to make their lives
better. And the problem it solves is
when you're building SAS or an AI
product and you want to sell to other
companies, there's all these
requirements you need to meet. There's
SSO, there's skim, there's arbback,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate but aren't
the main focus of your app. Work OS is
an API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So let's say you have a new SAS
product and you want to sell to other
companies. Work OS will solve all of
these critical feature gaps for you. You
can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast. Jira
byatlassian isn't just for tracking work
anymore. Now you can pick your favorite
AI agent to assign tasks to and they'll
get access to the rich context that's
already in Jira. When the agent is done,
it surfaces a poll request. That way you
can get more done with your favorite
agents all in one place. Learn more at
jira.dev. That's jir.dev.
Appreciate them for sponsoring the
podcast. And back to the show. [snorts]
Earlier we talked about the the
trade-off between I guess performant
code and maintainable code and I saw you
had this one video said you know in
quotes clean code horrible performance
I feel like this is on the same topic.
What's your your take there on you know
because you also put clean code in
quotes. What does that mean?
>> So it's a it's a fairly subtle topic
right? Uh, and that's why the the quotes
are there because um the first thing
that I you have to point out is that
clean code is clean code,
object-oriented programming, a lot of
these phrases, they mean different
things to different people. And so if
you're going to say that you're, you
know, this code is clean, it's pretty
hard to find two programmers who will
agree on exactly whether it is or not,
right? Like like they all have like
different ideas about what is clean and
what is not,
>> right?
So the reason I put that in quotes is I
was talking about a very specific thing
which is like literally like the book
clean code like the thing where there's
like here are the things that we would
recommend that you do right so in that
particular case what I was talking about
is there's a certain set of ideas that
is advocated in clean code as like these
are the things you should do and they
are like you should have uh everything
should be kind of um I guess I would say
dynamic dispatch or at least You
shouldn't code shouldn't know the types
it's operating on. Right? Saying it's
dynamic dispatch is maybe it depends on
the language whether that's going to be
true or not. But when I write code I
don't know what types I have. It's just
I don't know like some base classes is
what I'm operating on and they could be
anything. Right? That's thing one. Thing
two is functions should be very small.
Uh in fact the the numbers are kind of
weird. They're like four lines or five
line. Like when you go look at the
actual things that are claimed in some
of the this literature it's it's really
strange. you're just like, gosh, that's
very small, right? Um, and I go through
some of those things and I say, look, if
we were to actually follow these, we get
into a really bad state because a lot of
the languages that people are going to
be using to implement this stuff, like
C++ for example, um, which even would be
a fairly good case in a lot of because
at least it's a compiled language and so
on.
In a a lot of cases, these things are
kind of a recipe for disaster if you're
if you're handing out types where you
can't know the type at compile time or
you can't know the type uh or it's or
it's you know going to be in a different
module. So, you know, unless you have
like a really aggressive link time code
generation, it's not going to be likely
that you could figure this out and
you're saying all the functions should
be very small and of course they're
going to be virtual because they're on
these sort of types that you don't know
what they are.
This creates a really uh toxic
combination for the compiler. Normally
you can have I mean you can have small
functions if you want them only four
lines long. If the compiler can know
that it can just inline that, right? If
it can see clearly what you're doing and
it can just merge those things in, we
don't have a problem. If they're behind
a virtual function, so it doesn't know
like it can't guarantee that it is that
type. Um it can't do that. And so when
you talk about all this stuff, what
you're what you're giving up people I
think also because the video I mean the
video was a very short video as part of
like a series
I think people sometimes get the wrong
idea that I think that virtual function
calls cost a lot. They do cost something
but you know depending on how you want
to look at it they actually don't cost
that much. Uh because you know it
depends on whether it's predicted
correctly or not but in general like the
cost of virtual function is less than
you would think. A lot of times
the actual reason that it slows things
down is because the compiler cannot
merge the code together, right? It can't
inline stuff and remove and reduce the
waste. Like that's the actual problem.
So if you just want to call a virtual
function, yeah, it if it was a really
really uh hardcore optimization
scenario, then you don't want anything
probably calling a virtual function in
general because there is some cost to
that. Just calling a function has cost.
But that wasn't the really bad part of
it, right? So, it's that plus there's an
additional thing which is that it can't
unroll and go wide on things. If the
compiler can see everything you're
doing, it can use SIMD. It can like
widen loops to operate on multiple
things at once. It can unroll those
loops. There's all these things it can
do. If it's got these virtual functions,
it's just like that's it. I don't know.
I I can't make decisions about that. I
have no idea what this thing on the
other end is doing. Right? So, uh that
was kind of my point on that. And uh
again I it's not meant to be uh
assailing the idea that your code should
be easy to read or easy to maintain.
It's just more like these guidelines
seem really bad. And also I don't think
we need them for code to be
maintainable. I I don't have trouble
maintaining functions that are 30 lines
long or 50 lines long. I don't find that
five is a magic number or something or
that has to be really short. Uh and also
I find that it's usually pretty easy to
write code where I know what the types
are. Um that those can be determined at
compile time. Like I don't think that
results in code that's particularly hard
to read.
>> When I was in college very and very
early I remember people recommend that
book say oh you should read clean code.
>> So my understanding that you wouldn't
recommend people who are software
engineers to read that.
>> I guess the way I would categorize it's
a mixed bag. So I would I wouldn't
actually say that I disagree with all
all of the things in the book though. I
mean some of the things are things that
I definitely do myself like giving um
variables like easy to understand names
uh is something that I think would be
and that's in that book uh is good
advice right and so kind of more I
wouldn't I wouldn't necessarily say do
or don't read a book what I would say is
like I think there's some things in this
book that don't that aren't addressed
properly like I don't think you want to
tell people these rules of thumb and not
tell them about these other problems
That was exactly what I was uh pointing
out there. And so usually it's more that
it's like
I find that often times there is this
tendency
um I guess I'll say to pretend
that
we don't have to talk about performance
and we can just say like in fact
premature optimization is root all evil.
Bringing it back to there. I feel like
there's this uh temptation and very
prevalent practice of sort of taking
that idea to mean we don't have to talk
about performance when we're teaching
people things at all. Or like when you
write the book clean code, you don't
have to talk about performance at all.
can just include a thing that's
basically like hey um you know there's
performance issues but most of the time
it's not a problem or something like
that which is you know or if you look at
uh refactoring the book refactoring very
popular it literally says exactly that
in like the opening thing it's like you
know there there might be performance
concerns but you know they're usually
okay or something right and it's like
that is not true I just think that's
fundamentally not true I think these
books should include detailed
discussions of the actual performance
problems that you are very likely to hit
if you take some of their advice. Um
because it's not that it means you can't
do those things, but I'll quote you back
to you. It's about trade-offs. There is
always a trade-off that you're making.
And sometimes if you understand the
trade-off, you will make it. You'll say,
I know this is going to cost this may be
a serious performance problem for us,
but I think that's okay. Like I think
it's not like our performance won't
suffer to the point where it's a problem
for the product. I understand what
that's is. There's a huge difference
between that and just going like ah we
don't worry about performance till the
end, right? Like there's it's completely
different, right? Those are two
different engineering approaches. Uh and
so what I try to do is encourage people
to put that analysis back in, understand
the performance trade-offs you're
making, understand how much it might
cost in the future to like make these
fixes. And I I don't really do any AI
stuff, but my sort of feeling is more so
now than ever, I feel like that's got to
be pretty important because you're
instructing these AIs to do what they're
going to do. And I feel like it would be
a bad idea to not know about performance
trade-offs because especially if an AI
is going to be doing your bidding and
structuring the code the way you want to
structure it or doing whatever. It seems
like a very straightforward part of the
process to include performance stuff in
those instructions, right? Like that
would be a natural thing that we would
want to understand and do, right? So I
feel like
really I've been just trying to get that
more into the conversation. Uh, and I
feel like it's it's as relevant now as
it ever was, and arguably maybe more so.
I don't know, but I could be wrong about
that.
>> What are some things that are in your
mind, they're those high value
performance things to consider that
don't cost a whole lot to think about?
>> So, to me, awareness is the number one
thing, right? Understanding roughly the
performance characteristics of the
hardware that you're working on. Uh,
which includes things like, you know, if
there's a network, like what does that
look like? and so on. Um, it's really
about awareness more than anything else
because a little bit of awareness can go
a very long way. If you understand the
basic concept that like you know a that
network latency versus network
throughput are different things, you can
make upfront decisions about structuring
code such that you batch things properly
uh and so on and so forth. If you don't
understand those things, you could get
very far down a project only to realize
that everything you designed and all the
way it works is all very serial and
really just cannot be accelerated over a
network at all. Like it's never going to
run uh reasonably or something like
this, right? Uh and so I think the the
lowest hanging fruit is just to get some
education in performance. like get some
education in how to think about the way
a machine works and what makes it fast
or slow, what it struggles with and what
it doesn't and just to keep that in the
back of your head because at the end of
the day, if you have that knowledge, I
think you're very unlikely to make the
kinds of architectural decisions that
will be hard to undo later, right?
Um, and so that's really that's really
the majority of it I think and that is
by far the highest impact lowest cost
thing you can do is just do that
training once because once you have it
it's with you forever once you
understand how to think about
performance it can always be there and
at any time you can sort of have that
alarm bell of like this I don't see you
know you're always kind of looking like
I don't see the path towards this
running well and then So that's that
your key to stop and go like uh maybe we
need to rethink like how we were making
some of these decisions. As long as you
can see that path, you're pretty you can
you can delay most like optimization
work. As long as you can see the path
like here is how we will optimize this.
You're in pretty good shape because um
if you're making those trade-offs
correctly, you're not going to paint
yourself into a corner where there's
nothing that you can do other than scrap
and rewrite. Right. you had this one
video title. It said, you know, where
does bad code come from? And so, yeah,
[laughter] you know, I guess, yeah, my
question to you is, you know, what's the
answer to that? Where where does bad
code come from?
Yeah, that's a good question. Um, my
feeling on where bad code comes from is
that for everything that I've seen on
projects in the past, the bad code all
seems to come from roughly the same
source. And that is not dealing with the
actual thing that's happening, right? Um
there's a lot of ideas in computer
science about sort of doing upfront
design and making a lot of decisions
without ever really implementing
anything, right?
And I have found that universally that
leads to the worst kind of code. And the
reason for that is, you know, uh I hate
to be pessimistic and I hate to be
pessimistic about my own ability, but
I'll just say for me personally,
I am not able to correctly hold all of
the details for most complex software in
my head at once. There's just a lot of
stuff going on at like when when the
actual, you know, instructions hit the
CPU. There's a lot going on down there
that's very hard to keep all in your
head. And so when you approach an
upfront design, typically unless the
problem is very is like stupidly simple,
right?
When you approach something with upfront
design and you think you're going to get
all of this architecture worked out
ahead of time, you forget some important
things. You make decisions without
realizing, oh wait, there's this thing
that has to happen there that means that
this isn't really the right way for
these pieces of code to interoperate.
And so then you, you know, you end up
seeing these hilarious APIs or something
where it's like you're just like, how
did this end up being the way that you
do this, right? Like I have to create
all these objects and I have to connect
them together with these things and I
have to create this weird like filter
graph thing and then I have to call
compile on it. but only like you end up
with these like insane things. You're
like all I wanted to do was call this
one thing that said like low pass filter
this buffer. It could have been one
function call, right? It's like how did
you get there? And the answer is because
you weren't actually like dealing with
the actual problem and looking at what
the actual code looks like uh when you
want to actually uh when you actually
want to solve the problem in practice.
And so my idea of where bad code comes
from is usually just it's that it's this
failure to engage with the actual
reality of the situation.
Um
maybe there are people out there I
certainly have never met any but maybe
there are people out there whose brains
are so expansive that they can actually
hold all that in there and they can
therefore just do it upfront. Um, but
other than for very sort of constrained
problem spaces, I've never seen that
work. And and you know there, like I
said, there are sometimes when that's
the case with the trans like if you're
just doing like I'm trying to do this
particular mathematical operation, that
might be a case where you can work it
all out on paper because it's very
specific like what it is. It takes these
n inputs, produces this output, and I
can work right. But when you're talking
about architecture like, hey, it's a web
browser, right? Some complicated thing.
The details are all that matter to me,
right? It's like it's where all the
complexity lies and if you try to do the
design without reckoning with them, it
just leads to bad results in my
experience. So,
>> so how do you avoid writing bad code in
that case?
>> I I try to start with the actual
solutions to the problems and work up
from there. So, um
one way to say it would be instead of
top down programming, bottom up
programming, right? Uh as much as
possible. And top down programming isn't
really the same as designing up front,
but you know, I'm just saying like as a
contrast there, try to start with the
things that you know you need. Like it's
like, okay, if I'm if I'm building this
thing, it's got to have a rasterizer.
All right, I'm going to start making a
rasterizer. I'm going to see what kinds
of stuff that does and how I would like
what's the most uh straightforward way
to call this and use it. Okay, let's
make an API out of that, right?
build it out of steps where the
abstraction comes from actual working
code that gets abstracted rather than
pushing the abstraction down from the
top where I say this is how I will
abstract the rasterizer and now I go
write the rasterizer in the thing that
uses the rasterizer only to find that
that is not a very good way to use a
rasterizer right like so to me starting
with that and working upwards is the
best way to ensure that you will get an
architecture uh that is at least good
for one thing. Now, if you want it to be
good for multiple things, you probably
need a couple different like I want a
few different varied things that would
use this rasterizer that I will kind of
work on together and I'll make
abstraction decisions that work across
all three of them. That's a good way to
make a more reusable API that works for,
you know, a lot of things. But I never
want to just sit down and say, "How will
I design an API for lots of people to
use a rasterizer without actually
writing any of it?" It's like, "No, no,
no." Like, and I definitely can't do it.
And I I question I I would question
someone who says that they can, unless
one caveat, they've written a lot of
them before, right? If you've written
tons before, then you've sort of done
the thing that I'm talking about already
and you might remember, oh, it's this
way, right?
I think there's a lot of common advice,
especially at these these larger
companies where there's this processes
to, you know, write a design doc and
kind of uh, you know, put together
everything in advance, present it before
you write any code. And sounds like
you're saying that that's a terrible
idea.
>> I think that's an absolutely terrible
idea. Now, that doesn't mean that I
wouldn't be okay with that process with
like a slight modification, right? If
what you're doing during that time is
writing test code in the way that I'm
saying, so we're going to write a little
experimental rasterizer. We're going to
do those things. We're going to start
and then our document that we're
producing is here is what we have
determined is a good API based on these
experiments. I have no problem with
that. That's really that's following my
procedure pretty much to a tea. And you
know, I don't tend to produce
documentation because I work you know in
on smaller teams. I don't have to have a
thousand person org know exactly what it
what I'm doing there or whatever.
So I wouldn't produce upfront
documentation normally in a in a case
like that. But if you if you wanted to
that seems totally reasonable, right?
And that like is communicating our
research into how this should be
structured uh out to a wider audience.
But we still did the due diligence of
determining that it really does work in
practice. It's not just our guess about
what it will be.
>> I see. Okay. So you're saying kind of
this u pair design, pair prototype kind
of, you know, like you just build as you
go, but it's just so you get a sense of
the reality of the design.
>> Yeah. And I think I would be very
comfortable with the team that wanted to
work that way if they're like, look, we
want to produce, we want to document
this thing before we start developing
it. That's just how we feel more
comfortable, you know, with how we're
going to do it. Maybe it's a very large
org. Maybe we have some very good
reasons for that. Um, then I would say
totally fine. It's just I want I want to
hear you know if I'm going to be
comfortable with it I want to hear that
that process is not we're just typing on
paper. We are actually testing these API
uh design decisions and they come from
looking at actual usage code that we
have made and that we have implemented
at least uh experimental versions of so
that we know they really do account for
all the details that we're likely to
encounter in practice. That's what I
want to hear, right? I don't want to
hear like ah we thought it through. Like
I'm like did you did you think it all
the way through? Because I've seen a lot
of times where people thought they did
and they didn't including myself. Like
that is not that is not a I always think
it all the way through. So it's like no
this comes from a personal place of I
forgot the thing. Like I forgot this
important thing and I made a really
stupid design. Right.
>> There's another video you had. It was it
was titled the only unbreakable law.
>> Oh yeah.
>> And you know what is the only
unbreakable law in software engineering?
So yeah, that was that was a a lecture I
did um where I was trying to think of
like if I was going to say one thing
about architecture to people, right? If
I was going to say one thing about
architecture,
what could I say that isn't probably
wrong? Because you think about a lot of
our ideas about architecture, it's like
even the stuff I just said to you, who
knows what we're going to be thinking 10
years from now. It's like they're not
really laws. They're just
they're observations that we've had that
maybe this is a good way to do things,
but it's not really a law. Right? So, uh
the only thing I've seen that feels like
a real law to me is the thing I cover in
this lecture, which is Conway's law. Uh
and this is a a it's not a real law in
the sense of like the laws of gravity or
so like it's not a physics law like a a
physicist would laugh at calling it a
law. um you know, it's probably not even
a theory. It's more like a hypothesis at
this point, right? But in terms of
things that I would place money on
being validated as a law at some point
if we ever had the means to do so. This
would be one of the only software
engineering things that I think uh would
qualify and it is
that if you would like to organize
a series of like a set of people to work
on something or in the modern parliament
let's say agents. So it could be, it
doesn't have to be a human. It's any
system that has sort of its own internal
processing like a human brain does or
like a computer does.
If you need to partition a problem into
a set of workers in this way
where the communication between those
workers is slower than their own
internal computation ability, which we
would all agree is true about humans.
It's true about two computers running an
AI model as well, right? the amount of
time it takes to send information back
and forth to them is is significantly
slower than what like the GPU can be
processing directly on it on its own.
Right? In systems that look like that,
when you start to tackle a problem, in
order to get the benefits of that
parallelization,
you will have to make decisions about
who is working on what. At least some
decision. For example, if we're making a
car and you and I are the two people are
going to make the car, I'm going to
design the body of the car. you're gonna
design the wheels,
right? Just a decision someone could
make.
Once you've made that decision,
you have now locked in the fact that the
iteration
on the design
will be slower across that boundary than
it is interior to either of the two
parts. So for example, your ability to
improve the design of the wheels on
their own and my design ability to
design the body of the car uh and
improve that on its own will be much
faster than our ability to design the
interface between the wheels and the
tire like or or it's not even just the
interface. The
degree of harmony between the designs.
So the degree to which your wheels
complement my body design and my body
design complements your wheels that they
there's that they all are considering
the trade-offs together right
and Melvin Conway's paper which lays
this out uh this is a very early paper
it's you know it's in the 60s at least
was it in the 50s it's it's way back
when that lays this out points out the
consequence of this is that products
or any and when I say product I mean
anything that comes out of one of these
design processes or development
processes. Products will will have a
similar structure to the organization
that produced them. You will be able to
see in the product evidence of this
because the degree to which things are
able to harmonize is restricted across
that boundary. So when you look at the
object, it will have that boundary
visible in some way, right? It won't be
quite as good at the interface between
these two things or in the way that they
work together as the things are
themselves in inside like to themselves,
right?
And it gets sort of flattened like one
way the the rule is pithly stated is
like products look like the org chart,
right? But that's not exactly what it
says, but that's kind of a downstream
consequence. And boy, do you ever see it
in the real world. So, you know,
>> I've heard that in in the context of
these big tech companies, like almost
like it's a like a bad thing to quote
unquote ship your org chart or
basically, you know, the product you put
out there is has these uh inorganic
>> Yes.
>> You know, things. So, it sounds similar
to what you're saying.
>> Yeah. It's And I think like part of the
reason I think it is kind of an
unbreakable law is I think it's somewhat
unavoidable. uh it's more something that
you just have to be aware of and
mitigate to the degree that you can like
you just have to understand look that
lower communication time uh whether it's
humans or computers or whoever is doing
this work that lower communication time
uh or I should say that uh that lower
communication bandwidth is what um that
just means that we will like where we
draw these lines has consequences for
what we ship And so we really want to
try over time to align those boundary
drawings
to places where it will have the least
bad impact on the result of the product.
And you know that's true for org charts.
Like I said, I suspect it will also
become true for AIs and things like that
where it's like you will want to
partition these problems in ways that
respect that um that line drawing
because that will be less good than the
thing that can be wholly solved um you
know by one one unit whatever that unit
is. And so to me uh it's a very helpful
construct for thinking about things.
It's also a very good explanation for
why you see some things somewhere you're
like why isn't this just integrated in
this? It's like because they were two
different teams,
>> you know? It's like I'm sorry. Like I'm
so like I'm sorry that's just the
answer. And you know, it costs a lot
more for those two teams to have
integrated this. That's not how we work,
right?
>> I I'd love to hear more about I guess
your career and how you got into
programming.
>> I started programming when I was really
little because my father worked at
Digital Equipment Corporation, which is
actually a very important company in
that era. no longer exist, right? This
was the they would they would be sort of
like almost like a case study in how not
adapting to a change in technology uh
leads to your demise. They were one of
the most important companies in the
world for computing. If you ever heard
of a PDP11 or a vax in computing
history, that's them, right? They made
these things that were foundational
computers in computing history gone
today, right? they were uh part of them
got absorbed by Intel, part of them got
absorbed by Compact, but they're they
don't exist.
So he worked for that company
and so we always had computers in the
home and I learned to program when I was
little and that's just sort of always
what I wanted to do. I really enjoyed it
and so I ended up uh getting an
internship at Microsoft when I was
pretty young and I met some people
there. I came out to I I should say I
grew up on the east coast so nowhere
near Microsoft. Um I met some people
there. I ended up coming out to the west
coast really early on. This would be in
like 95. Uh so what didn't feel early at
the time. It felt late in the computer
history but nowadays it's like oh wait
95. Oh my god. Like before before
everything was on the web, right? Uh I
ended up there was a web though. It was
it was nent. Um, I ended up uh coming
out and and working sort of in the game
industry and that's what I did ever
since. And I've mostly always worked on
game technology. I'm famously like
absolutely terrible at understanding
game design. Uh, people who watch my
stuff know this about me. Like I'm very
very bad at I've tried to make games a
couple times and I'm just I just cannot
do the design side. I'm awful at it. Uh,
but I really enjoy the engine stuff and
I've I've uh feel like I I'm o okay at
it and I've been able to contribute to
projects. Um, so in general, most of the
time if you've used code that was
written by me, you probably uh used it
in the context of like a video game that
was using technology that I wrote. And
so, you know, an example would be um I
worked at Rad Game Tools on a character
animation system. Uh, I wrote the entire
thing myself that is used well, that's
not entirely true. I really think myself
except for the texture compressor which
uh Jeff Roberts wrote. There was like
this texture compressor that you could
use um as part of the pipeline for the
exporting and stuff like that.
And it was a pretty cool project at the
time. Um I'm really proud of it. The
first version was awful uh as it is
because I was pretty new at the time.
The second version I thought we did a
really nice job. And it was made at a
time when people didn't think you could
do licensable game technology of that
kind because it was too hard to
integrate into things like you couldn't
get the performance or whatever. And we
did a lot of things that I think were
pretty innovative at the time and we
were able to make something that was
very successful. And it's uh I mean we
released the first version of that in
99. It's still in use today, largely
unchanged from the architecture that I
guess was the second version I did in
like 2001 or something. Um, there are a
few changes to architecture that people
have made over the times, but it's
largely unchanged. And I mean like I
found out recently Balders's Gate 3,
which was a big game um from Larian came
out. I had no idea. It turns out they
still use they use it, right? It's in
their engine or whatever. So, I'm very
proud of that product because I think it
it it was in tons of games and was a
very hard problem to solve and I think
we solved it pretty well. It's largely
irrelevant today. I would say it's still
in some people's like engines over time,
but like it's not the kind of product
you would make today because nowadays
engines are monolithic and you license
them as a whole typically, right? Like
you you wouldn't be getting like a
character animation library. it's going
to be something that's like built into
Unreal Engine or built into Unity,
right? So, it's not the kind of product
you would probably consider making
today. So, that that was mostly um like
in terms of things that I've done that
people might have actually have
experienced or used.
Uh like folks at home, if you've played
games, you may have played something
that I had a hand in at some point, but
only the technology, not the design. Uh
I also worked uh a little bit on The
Witness um which was a game by Jonathan
Blow uh and and team uh that I thought
was absolutely fantastic and I did some
work on uh I did some work on the walk
system there that I was I was pretty
proud of. I thought it came out pretty
well. There's there's some parts of it
that are really janky. I I don't think I
did a very good job of the actual
implementation of it, but the design was
pretty good. Let's put it that way.
>> Early in your career, so you worked at
Microsoft and then and then you went to
go
>> I I was only ever an intern. I never
actually like I mean I guess that's
technically working there but I I didn't
ever work there as like an employee
employee right
>> as a someone who's writing code. I mean
there's a lot of different paths but
there's one one path I imagine is you go
and you work at one of these big tech
companies and create their tech products
I guess and then video gaming seems like
another path and I think there's other
paths as well of course. Um, what drew
you to, you know, going towards video
gaming and, you know, not continuing
down a Microsoft path or something like
that?
>> I think that there's a bunch of things I
could say about that, but they're
probably all BS.
The truth is probably that I'm probably
more uh affected by the people around me
than I would like to admit. I mean, I
guess I don't have a problem aditting it
now, but I mean, at the time, I probably
wouldn't have have said that, right? I
could envision a alternate past where I
did stay at Microsoft and, you know, try
to get a job there and work there
instead of being just an intern and then
going off and working at a different
place.
The reason that didn't happen was
because of the people who I worked with
there when I was an intern. I
fundamentally really like like nowadays
I fundamentally really love doing things
like you know analyzing assembly code or
looking at exactly how a micro
architecture is working and these sorts
of things. If I had gone to Microsoft
and had just happened to be under some
people who were doing that kind of work
and had like taught me how to write like
device drivers in assembly language or
something like that, I I might still be
there today. Right? That's not what
happened. The capsule summary is the
group that I was supposed to be in. The
way that they did internships at that
time was that a set of interns, say uh
three or four of them would be uh
underneath a particular manager who was
going to like be managing those interns.
So there were a couple of us who were
supposed to be reporting to to this guy
whose name I won't mention just in case
for some reason. It's ancient. He
probably wouldn't care at this point,
but we're supposed to be reporting to
this particular person
and literally the week before we arrive,
he has this massive flame out with upper
management,
leaves like just walks out of the
building and has not been heard from
since.
So we show up and it's me um there was
like uh me this a guy named Rudy a guy
named Rajie uh and we're just interns
show up we're like hey how's it going
and we we report to this test guy this
an SD uh guy named um Scott Leam really
nice guy
and we're like we're supposed to be like
reporting to like a like a program like
a you know a software or like what's
going on like this one of the guys in
the test or he's like, "Yeah, that that
[laughter] guy's gone, right?" Like,
he's out of here, right? Uh and and me
and this other guy, Bruce Johnson, are
going to like take care of the interns
because
right, we don't really know what you're
going to do. Uh the first thing I think
Bruce Bruce had me do was like an ANI
cursor loader. There was there's this
format I don't know uh ancient history
now, but there's this format for
animated cursors on Windows. If you ever
see the stupid little walking dinosaur
or the like this is no one uses these
anymore, I don't think, but they were
this thing that were in was in there. He
had me write a parser for loading ANI
files, right? Like it's just meaningless
stuff. Uh, so my experience there was
pretty lame. Like I was like, this is
kind of dumb. Like I don't really want
to work here, right? But it could have
been totally different. Like if I had
been on some team that had like really
inspired me to like learn the stuff that
I didn't know. I didn't know assembly
language at that time really at all. I
think the only thing I'd ever written
assembly language was a joystick pulling
routine for DOSs because the only way
you could pull the joy joystick in DOSs,
right? And I think that's really it. If
I'm honest about it, I think most of it
is that I think when you're even if
you're a very brash youngster, which I
was, and even if you think that you're
very independent,
um I think you definitely
gravitate towards people who you see
doing things you think are impressive
or, you know, technologically
interesting.
And that is just not the experience I
had at Microsoft. Now, there were some
people who I like the people I went out
to go work with were people in other
parts of Microsoft who were leaving
Microsoft to do like a startup company,
right? And those were the people that I
was really like impressed with. Like
those were the people that I wanted to
hang out with. So like if I just look at
it in a rears like if those people had
just been staying at Microsoft and doing
something maybe I would have gone,
right? And I think that's the truth of
it as best I can determine at this
point. Anyway,
>> so you moved across the country to go
and work with those people at a startup.
>> Yes.
>> That's feels pretty risky uh to do. You
know,
>> it it was especially because at that
time a startup is not really what you
think of as a startup today. Like
startup is just like some scrappy people
in like a crappy office doing stuff.
Like nowadays you think startup it's
like well we've got $10 million in VC
funding and we you know like have free
sodas and what like in the break room
and a massage uh a masseuse comes in
periodically or something like this
right like I don't know what the what
the now version of a startup is but it's
very different right um so yeah it was
it was pretty risky and I don't really
know why I did it it was mostly just
because I hadn't had really good
experiences with education like I didn't
really want to to do um like college or
like I I didn't want to do any more
education. Like I wanted to actually
work for whatever reason and this seemed
like a this was just the easiest way to
do that. And I don't really regret it
honestly. Um,
I've been able to learn most of the
things that I would have needed to like
if I was going to go do a PhD or
something like I've ended up doing work
that I that is the sorts of stuff like
I've I've been lucky enough to be in
positions where I could go spend, you
know, a few months writing like this,
you know, uh, this particular like
linear lease squares solver or something
like that like the kinds of things you
might have done as like a thesis or
something. uh or or you know that that
walks somebody might have done the
witness those sorts of things are the
kinds of things you would have done had
you decided to get a master's degree or
something like that so I'm fortunate
enough that I've kind of been able to
have that part of the education um
because not everyone gets that
opportunity like you may never get you
know if you if you don't do a master's
thesis or you don't do a PhD thesis you
may never really get the chance to like
really do a deep like work on a on one
problem and like learn a lot about it,
read a lot of papers, do you know may
maybe make some novel contribution in in
some very small way usually, right? But
um and so that that I was just lucky
enough to do. So I don't really regret
not doing something like that. But I
think you know had I not had that those
opportunities and subsequently I could
see being I could see being regretful
about that because that is something
that I do enjoy doing and if id never
had the chance I would have been sad. So
you you went and you traveled to this
startup
because there's there's no there's no
funding it sounds like. So yeah, what
did you So it's just a group of guys
just was there pay or it's just
>> not really no it was it was pretty
rough. Uh and I it didn't last very
long, right? Um I ended up going to work
at an actual game company shortly after
that called Gaspired Games. And then
shortly after that I started work at Rad
Game Tools which I stayed at for quite
some time uh and where I did like that
character animation system and stuff. So
it was it was pretty quick into not
doing that. But um it was still a pretty
educational experience for me. And also
uh what I will say is um at the time so
uh I worked with there a guy named Chris
Hecker who uh I have to give like
basically complete credit to for
teaching me basically about like reading
technical papers.
Like before that time, I just thought
math was kind of stupid and an annoying
thing you had to do like in class,
right? And I I definitely didn't know
anything about like
reading a sigraph's proceedings really,
right? Um and I may have been like aware
I mean I was aware of sigraph. I knew
what it was, but I don't think if you'd
handed me, you know, that binder, I
would have known what that was or what
to do with it. like, you know, I think
like the biggest takeaway that I got
from that other than startups are hard
and maybe don't do them uh unless you
have a lot of people and a lot of
funding and aren't really that much on
the line like maybe uh but uh the
biggest takeaway that I got from that
that was positive was just a a a much
deeper appreciation for math, a much
deeper appreciation for research, how to
read it. Um, that's where I learned to
use like Sightseer, which would be like
kind of the precursor to like Google
Scholar or whatever, crawling references
and all that stuff. In a lot of ways,
you could say, uh, if I hadn't had that
experience, I bet I wouldn't have given
the two talks that we've talked about
for most of the interview because what
are those talks? They're me crawling
every reference, right? They're just me
going back and back and back and back
and looking at everything that I can
find. Um, and that's something that if
you if no one ever conveys to you the
importance of reading the scholarship
and being aware of what's being done and
also teaches you how to read a tech
paper and how to parse through it. I I
don't know that you get that, you know,
I don't know that you get that.
>> I remember early in my career, I think
there's this, I guess, common path of
like these, you know, big companies and
then there's this thought of, oh, me and
a couple buddies, let's go, let's go
build [laughter] something. Now, now
with your experience looking back, if
you someone out there's uh young and
thinking about starting, would you say
go that common path or would you say
take the the chance?
>> You know, uh it's a really tough
question and I think that the advice
like the advice is that you have to
think about what it is that you want to
do every day. Like, so in my mind, the
things I regret are the times when I've
had to do things or chosen to do things
that I wasn't really that happy doing
every day, right?
And so I think you just have to optimize
for the experience you want to have
because a startup might work out, it
might not. It's always a risk, right?
You may go to the big company um and you
know it may be cool, there may be
interesting things there or there might
not be. like who know like you don't
really know you're making a kind of
blind decision
and so I think you kind of have to
optimize for what do you want your
dayto-day to be like like what do you
want the experience to be and you want
to like keep a running t like you want
to be aware of it like if you make a
decision and six months in you are not
liking what you're doing every day then
you need to get out of that right like
that's my opinion
so I don't know I I think most people
probably if they sit down and actually
like clear their mind and aren't aren't
engaging in too motivated a reasoning
but just for themselves go what do I
envision working at the startup will be
like what will I actually be doing every
day like am I going to like that is this
going to be thrilling like trying to
make this thing work and like being kind
of on the edge um and you know uh do I
want the the kind of war stories of like
the things we had to do to pull off the
demo or whatever, right? If all that
sounds exciting to you and you want to
have that experience, then you should do
that thing. And and and I would say like
really I really mean that like I don't
even think you should take into account
like even like let's say you know the
startup's going to fail. If that's if
you want to have that experience then
you need to do it, right? It's just like
anything else. It's like going and um
backpacking across Europe or playing
guitar at a nightclub. It's like you may
know that these things are not
profitable.
It's just is that the experience you
want to have? Are you going to look back
on that six months or a year or five
years or whatever the amount of time
you're thinking of committing to it? Are
you going to look back and say I'm glad
I did that or are you going to be like
that was the you know those that's time
that I would have rather have spent some
other way, right? And so I think most
people can probably if they're honest
with themselves at least make a pretty
good guess. And that guess if they're
honest with themselves is going to be
better than any advice I'm going to give
them. like my guess about what you
should do is going to be worse than
yours. So, you should just make that uh
determination because another way to
look at it is like you know that the big
company side is like maybe you just want
to have some security like maybe when
you're starting out like I mean I'll
just give some examples like maybe you
want to uh spend a lot of time dating.
You want to you want to uh find a
partner and you want to have a
relationship and you want to have a
family.
Maybe that's more important to you.
Maybe the startup yeah might be fun.
Maybe it would be more money if it
worked out or whatever, but like maybe
the stability is is actually going to be
something that that you would that that
you would really benefit from because
the sorts of things that you imagine
being fulfilling in your life are not
all around what you're going to be doing
in computing. I think you can know have
some guess about those things when you
if you just let yourself have some space
to think about it and don't engage in
too much motivated reasoning about it.
Right?
And uh and I think that would be the
best way to make a decision if you're
going to make one. That's my that's my
feeling about it. Anyway,
>> if we talked a lot about video game
engineering, and I have no idea what
goes into video games, if you were to
just boil it down to the the big pieces
that you need for a video game, what are
those software components?
So the biggest thing that's different
about a video game is that the sort of
original mental model that you're talked
that you're taught in programming which
is like the uh standard IO like I get
some input in I process it I put some
input out is like not how it works right
so the biggest mental shift is just like
oh the way that a video game or a
simulation of any kind right works is I
need to have some world state and I'm
constantly updating that world state on
a regular interval. Everything is always
happening. There's no I wait for input
and then I do something, right?
Everything is always going because it is
real time like the time is going um
forward. So the components tend to be
built around this idea and it depends on
what level of sophistication you end up
getting into but in general you need a
way of storing that world state. So some
kind of we usually call these entities.
um like the things that make up a world,
right? So, some way of modeling what is
in the world, where are things in the
world, what is their state, what are
they doing right now. So, you need
something that does that, something that
is in charge of advancing that state.
This is a mixture of several things. Uh
it could involve physical simulation. It
could involve AI. Uh not necessarily
like large language model like the
modern notion of AI, but like path
finding. uh making a decision between
whether I should attack the player or
not like that sort of AI, right?
Um
so we have the the world some way of
showing the world state, some way of
advancing the world state, like an
update step that may involve lots of
things like that.
Then some way of presenting the world
state. So a renderer, right? And this is
something that typically uh has
uh I guess I would say it's it's
traditionally been a very important part
of a game because the visuals are often
something that is a selling point for
games.
People produce trailers certainly in the
AAA space. We're trying to show you how
cool the new lighting looks and the
whatever. So that is a pretty big
component of games. Often times you go
look at an indie pixel art game, it
might be much smaller, right? Because
that's a much smaller part of the
problem. Now that's generally what what
you know the shape looks like. There's a
lot of little pieces there. Typically
nowadays we would have some way of asset
streaming, right? The the renderer needs
to have things like textures loaded,
models loaded, things like that. We need
world data, physics, collision models,
these sorts of things. they might be too
big to fit in memory or we don't want to
spend a lot of load time to load them up
front. We want to stream them in as
they're necessary. So there's typically
like this thing that's sitting there
constantly grabbing things off of disk,
caching things, pulling them in and out
of a cache that's being used uh by the
renderer, by the physics, so on. So
that's another common component that's
new, didn't used to be there. Um there's
going to be an audio and music system
obviously that's in charge of like you
know when sounds are triggered in the
world ambient sound effects that are
happening in the world music that's
playing continuity again all of that's
interacting with the entity with you
know the world state to know which ones
of those things are happening the update
step which will be triggering things in
that sound system and of course this the
asset streaming to load what sounds are
being played or load the music. So we
typically have that and then um you know
I'm trying to think not I'm trying not
to leave out any major components. In a
modern uh context there's often
networking. So we want to have a way for
multiple of these game clients to
communicate with a server. So typically
what that means is that world that uh
state of the world is now might be
provisional. It might be sort of a
predicted model of the world that's not
the real model of the world. the the
simulator is actually the authoritative
simulator is actually running on a
server somewhere and I am merely
communicating with it to find out what
the world state is and then because I
don't want to wait the late I don't want
the latency of like going all the way
around I am predicting the motion of
things forward in time based on the last
information I have right so that's
another kind of way that things tie in
if you want to start doing things like
competitive multiplayer and all these
sorts of things Right. That makes a lot
of sense because like I I used to play
video games and then like these MMO RP,
you know, online games and when I start
to lag, everyone continues forward.
>> Yes.
>> And then my internet catches up and then
everyone jumps to where they actually
supposed to be. Uh, okay. That makes a
lot of sense. I pulled some of your top
tweets. I thought it might be
interesting to kind of discuss.
>> I'm sorry. So [laughter]
you someone said NASA does not allow
recursion in their code. How crazy is
that? And then you said not even
slightly crazy. And it went really
viral. Can you explain why that's not
even slightly crazy?
>> When you're writing functions in a
programming in a procedural programming
language like we have uh and that like
NASA is probably using,
you are able to use the program stack
for storage. I mean, that's what it's
there for. That's what local variables
are. I call a function, I get some
storage space on the stack. The compiler
did that for me.
It also saves the return address. So,
when I make a function call, that
program stack is keeping track of where
in my code I was. So that when the thing
that I called is finished, I get back
there, not some other point. Right?
Neither of those two things are things
you couldn't implement yourself. Right?
They're both things you could do. You
could break the thing up into pieces.
You could have ways of remembering what
they were like a state machine. You can
have your own stack that you push data
on and access it. Right?
So the only thing recursion really does
is it allows you to leverage the fact
that someone already wrote that code for
you and it may be more convenient to use
because it's built into the language.
Now there are some things if you really
want to get super technical about it.
There are some things that happen at a
CPU level when functions are called but
we can put those aside for now. If you
want to talk about them after we totally
could. So the reason that I don't think
it's crazy to go like we're not going to
use recursion to implement an algorithm
is because if you're doing that you're
kind of just yolo swagging that there's
room on the stack for whatever it was
that you were doing, right? And you
can't even really check unless you're
going to do some kind of weird like we
could sort of do a thing where we go
like okay let's try to determine how
many more iterations how many more
recursion depths we have before we hit
the end of our stack. We can do those
calculations but it's like eh like and
also if the compiler changed something
about the layout it wouldn't be true
anymore and so on and so forth. So it's
like, so if I'm NASA and I'm like, hey,
I don't want my astronauts to crash into
the moon. It seems much more logical to
say like, don't use recursion. Just
figure out whatever this thing was that
you're going to do, turn it into a loop,
keep a stack, and make a state machine
for it. We can reason about that much
more clearly. We know exactly how long
it's going to take. It doesn't matter
what compiler gets. So it work the same
way every time, and we'll know the
bounds precisely, right? Very sensible
to me, right? And again, you assume at
NASA that they're not doing it for their
health. They're doing it because they
have, you know, hard constraints on the
problem domain where someone's life is
at risk. Um, and at or at a minimum many
millions of dollars in equipment is at
risk if you screw up. If if you stack
fall like if you if you get something
where you'd recursed too many times and
hit the end of the stack that is not
just a uh oh I rebooted the computer or
the re or restarted the software right
so so I don't know hopefully that makes
sense
>> Karpathy had this famous tweet that kind
of coined the phrase vibe coding
>> yes
>> and then you said if you thought
software was bad today buckle up because
it's about to get a whole lot worse.
Yes.
>> It's been about a year and a half since
that tweet came out. The tweet came out
February of 2025. Would you say that
that was an accurate prediction?
To be clear, I think
it the whole lot worse part is
predicated on something that may not
happen and that is that the idea that we
just kind of type some stuff into a
computer and ship it to prod, right?
Basically like, "Hey, could you make me
a thing?" and then publish it becomes a
common way of doing things, right? For
example, also done by people who maybe
don't have a computer science
background. I think it's fair to say and
that I wouldn't be uh being sort of
overly dismissive of AI at this point to
say that a person who is well-trained in
computer science using an AI to make
code right now can make substantially
better code than someone who doesn't
know anything about computer science who
is just given you know fable and types
some stuff in right the difference is
rather dramatic I would say from
everything that I've seen
So part part of my uh concern that I was
trying to express at that tweet was like
if the idea is like we're just going to
type stuff in and we're not going to
really be checking the code, you know,
someone who knows computer science is
not really going to be looking at it. Um
worst case scenario, it's literally just
like some random person in marketing
somewhere who has no idea what
programming is just types in and hits
crosses their fingers, right? I think
we're in for a world of hurt right now.
It's a race. So, it's hard to say
because it's basically a race of how
good can you make the AI versus how much
adoption does it get, right? It's a
curve, right? It's like if you can make
the AI good enough that the people who
are adopting it at a particular rate are
always using an AI that's good enough
for what they're adopting it for, we
wouldn't expect software to get
significantly worse. If those curves go
the other way, we're in a lot of
trouble, right? So, we're I feel like
right now we're we're almost kind of
teetering on this knife's edge. It's
it's really to me it feels like a foot
race of like improving AI so it can be
more autonomous and make better
decisions without your without you
needing to make them for it versus the
capability level of people who are using
it and the degree to which they're
paying attention to its output. It's
like these two curves that are just like
ah, you know, like what's [laughter]
what's gonna happen? I don't have a
prediction. I don't know where we'll be
in a year. Uh obviously for all of our
sake, I'm hoping that the AI curve wins.
Uh because I agree like I understand
certainly the perspective of people who
maybe just don't like AI and don't want
there to be AI. I can understand the uh
wanting it to fail. I I understand that,
right? Um and I'm no fan of AI myself,
so it's not like I like I'm going to
criticize someone for taking that
position.
But at the end of the day, if you're
talking about something that tons of
people are using,
you're gonna kind of want it to be good.
Like I think at this point given the
level of adoption of AI, I really don't
think it's would be great if it stopped
getting any better right now. Like if
this was as good as it was going to get,
I think that might be bad. Um certainly
six months ago, I think that was true.
Uh and I think it's probably still true
today. So I think ideally if you want
software to not be terrible, you have to
kind of still be hoping that six months
from now the AIs are again significantly
better than they were, right? Like that
that is the only way out of the current
situation as I see it, right? Uh I don't
know if that's fair, but that's my
that's my sort of feeling on that. One
of your other top tweets it was, you
know, Shopify put out this internal memo
and you just, you know, you replied, you
know, slopify. Yes. [laughter]
>> So, I guess it's cuz in this tweet, it's
leadership pushing the adoption curve
maybe harder than the capabilities of
the AI in this case.
>> Yeah. Uh, although I also just like the
bot. One of the things that I think is
most unfortunate about the AI adoption
as I've seen it is just the because
people think that it's going to be this
major um I guess if I had to categorize
the way it appears that companies are
reasoning about it. They're assuming
that if they don't get in early, it will
be a big disaster for them, right? like
like there's a tremendous like they
don't just think oh well we can just
wait until the AI does what we need it
to do and then start using it. They're
like, "No, we have to do it now." Like
even before we know whether it can
really do the thing that we want it to
do or whether we know whether the
outcomes will be good, everyone has to
do it right now. Let's do this. Right.
Um and I understand why they want why
they're going about it that way because
they think that that that is critical,
right? They obviously believe that's
very important.
Um, and to me that's just that's just
kind of terrifying because as with any
technology, the sane way to do it is to
measure its capabilities, see how well
it is able to solve problems that you
have, see if it solves them faster than
the way that you were do doing it, and
put it into a workflow at such a time as
you've determined that it is a net
positive. That's just the same like
that's what you do with any technology,
right? And you'd probably have like your
team of people whose job it is to assess
this thing and they're out there yolo
swagging it, right? They've got 3,000
agents working on this cluster talking
to each other and doing, you know, god
knows what, right? And uh so there's
going to be that and someone's going to
be doing that, but that is should not be
every or right like you wouldn't just be
like everyone needs to use a ton of
tokens, right? Um
so yeah, like I I do have concerns about
that. I don't think that that the way AI
adoption was done was was the best way
for quality in software. But I would
temper that statement with just the
obvious fact that like we were not
exactly a 59's uh industry to start out
with. Like software quality was really
pretty low rolling into the AI era. So I
always try to just also caveat most of
the things that I have to say that might
be critical of a particular thing
happening with AI with just the fact
that like look it wasn't particularly
great beforehand either. Uh a lot of
this software was pretty low quality and
so you can't
some AI things may may make things worse
but it's not like software was amazing
and the AI showed up and ruined
everything. That is completely
ridiculous narrative that that is not
true at all. Do you have any top
technical book recommendations for any
engineers that might be listening?
>> Uh, no. I would probably use this
opportunity to try to pitch reading
technical papers. I think something that
uh really the industry could use more of
is people being more aware of what's
happening um both like the historical
papers but also just current papers. Uh
it's daunting at first to be sure if you
don't tend to read technical papers in
your field. You will probably find it
confusing. You won't know where to find
them. You won't know how how to approach
them. Um it will seem to take too long
to read them because you don't know how
to like skim them properly and determine
whether it's worth your time to
investigate a particular section of a
paper and all that stuff. But if you're
willing to spend uh a few months of just
like I at night I look at a paper, you
know, or on my lunch break I look at a
paper, you know, if you're willing to
spend a few months of just doing that,
you will get your bearings and you will
start to know where the good papers are
in your field. You'll know how to find
them. You'll know what where they tend
to be published. Uh you'll be able to
read them much more effectively. You'll
be able to know how to spend your time
on them. And I think in all but probably
a few small fields that probably exist
somewhere that maybe people don't tend
to write much papers in or something
like that, it's tremendously valuable.
And I think it's so valuable that I read
papers in disciplines I don't even do
and I find it extremely rewarding. I I
read security research papers all the
time. I don't even work in a field where
there are security research
implications. Like games don't really do
much of that. that they tend to be run
like very sandboxed and they don't, you
know, sometimes there are, but they're
not that kind of thing. They're not like
a, you know, web server authentication
protocol or something like this.
Uh, and I just find it incredibly
rewarding because there's just so much
good stuff out there that you can learn.
So, I would say that would be it instead
of a book wreck. I would say find a
paper. Try reading a paper. How do I go
and find that, you know, first paper or
some place to get started that will be
valuable
>> for most people who are watching because
they they might be like generalists or,
you know, work work in in webdev or in
just a a tech general tech org at a at a
big tech company or something like that.
I would say like pull up the proceedings
of USNIX uh US NIX. Um
look through it for a paper that sounds
interesting to you and try reading that
paper or uh oftentimes there's a awards
I think USNIX has them where it's like
best paper of the conference. Try
reading the best paper conference. See
what you think. Um because that's like a
that's a collection of papers that's
usually about like operating system
stuff and you know systems design stuff.
So it's going to be something that most
people can relate to. It's not going to
be really esoteric like if you were to
open up the proceedings of sigraph for
example it'd be like oh uh you know
neural networks for cloth simulation or
something you're like okay like
this is not I can't relate to this
because I don't do graphics or whatever
right uh so usix might be a good place
to start um but in general yeah like if
you had another option would be to go to
scholar.google google.com
which is their search that just
specializes in like papers and type in a
topic description that you find
interesting. So like um if you wanted to
learn you know maybe maybe you were very
interested in consensus algor Paxos or
something and I don't know what that is
or I it came up at work and I haven't
really ever looked at it. You can just
type that in Paxos and it'll just be a
list of papers and they'll say a thing
like cited by you can see how many
citations they have. That's usually how
influential that paper was. Like I mean
to a certain extent. Um so you know
those are some ways you could get
started and find something that might
interest you. Uh and you know it won't
be for everyone. You may bounce off it
but it be that'd be my recommendation is
something to try. You you might you
might find it interesting.
>> And then yeah last question for you is
if you could go back to the beginning of
your career when you just entered the
industry and give yourself some advice
what would you say?
So I think the advice I would have given
to myself was to get into low-level
programming earlier.
Uh, I didn't really learn how to like
properly analyze and or even really
write assembly language code until
probably like
gosh 201 or 15 or like I mean it's
recent um because I'm pretty old and you
know it it's like last 10 years or so or
something, right?
And uh and I feel like I always
I always wanted to know how to do it and
just never seemed to. And like the the
advice I would have given to myself that
was like just just go like down the hall
like what I was interested like go down
the hall and like be like grab some be
like show me how the heck you write this
like just just show it to me. like
right. I think one of the problems is uh
a lot of people especially when they're
young they are afraid of appearing like
they don't know things and I think that
can be a real impediment to learning.
I'm sure it was for me and I probably
like just didn't want to like literally
say like I don't know I don't understand
any of this stuff like can you explain
it to me and uh and I think that's one
of the most useful things you can do
like I don't understand this please
explain it to me is very useful and most
people will be very happy to do that if
they're not a dick like most people will
be like oh sure like here you know um
now they might not be good at explaining
it there are plenty of engineers who are
like really good at something and suck
suck at like telling you how they do
what they do. So you won't always get a
great explanation, but sometimes you
will. Sometimes you'll find the type of
person who can explain very clearly how
it is they do what they do. So if just
keep asking, you'll get you'll get the
good explanation. Nowadays,
I wouldn't really need to give myself
exactly that advice because the internet
has so much great information on it. I
could have taught myself. That did not
exist at the time.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time, Casey. I really appreciate
it.
>> Thank you so much for having me. Like I
said, I love the show. It was it was an
honor to be invited on. So, thank you
very much.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
Guests like Barbara Liskov, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker, these were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. Um, this is in the
case, but yeah, we launched on
Kickstarter and we hit our goal within
eight hours of launching. I really
appreciate it if you were one of the
people who grabbed one of the early
units. Um, we're now working on the long
journey of building the tooling now. And
so, if you still want to pick one up,
I've left the late pledges open on
Kickstarter, so you can grab one there.
I'll put a link in the description.